地球脉动  III
这些人正在寻找
These people are hunting
地球上最濒危的动物之一
for one of the most endangered animals on the planet.
黑犀 一种因犀角而遭到偷猎的动物
The black rhino - an animal poached for its horn.
但这些人并不会伤害它
But they aren't going to harm her.
杜米 · 兹瓦内和他的团队正在执行救援任务
Dumi Zwane and his team are on a rescue mission.
我永远不会放弃为犀牛而战的信念
I don't think I'll ever stop fighting for rhino.
这是我的使命
It's just not possible.
好了
OK! Yeah...
他们正在安全保护区建立一个新的繁殖群
They're setting up a new breeding colony in a safe haven.
放在二号吊索上
Get her on two.
二号吊索 很好
Two. OK. That's good.
这只雌性黑犀将成为繁殖群的核心
This female is going to be at the very centre of it.
它重逾一吨
She weighs over a tonne...
出发
Go!
只有一种办法才能把它运走
..and there's only one way to get her out.
很好
That's it.
就是这样 很好
There we are. Perfect!
看着它这样飞走 我心情非常激动
When I watch it fly off, it's very emotional.
是一种无与伦比的感觉
It's a beautiful feeling.
它被注射了镇静剂 很安全
She is sedated and safe...
半小时内便会返回地面
...and in less than half an hour, she'll be back on the ground
在这个可能拯救整个物种的项目中 开始属于它的新生活
and starting a new life in a project that could save her entire species,
这一切都要感谢杜米和他的优秀团队
thanks to Dumi and his remarkable team.
家    园    卫    士
在20年前 我们开始制作
We started making the very first Planet Earth series
旁  白
大卫 · 爱登堡  爵士
《地球脉动》系列
just over 20 years ago.
自那时起 我们的摄影团队走遍了世界各地
Since then, our camera teams have filmed all over the world
调查了一些最原始 最偏僻的角落
and visited some of its wildest and most remote corners.
然而事实上 我们拍摄的大多数动物
But the truth is that most of the animals we filmed
都在这20年间变得越来越稀少
over these last two decades are now rarer than they were.
它们的生存家园
And the places where they live
也面临着越来越大的危机
are in greater danger of destruction.
但这些年 我也看到了另一种变化
But I've seen another change in those years,
一种充满希望的变化
a hopeful change.
一代杰出的人们正在挺身而出
A new generation of remarkable people are stepping up
拯救野生动物
to save wildlife.
他们克服巨大障碍
They're overcoming huge obstacles,
投身危险之境
travelling to dangerous places,
有时甚至冒着生命危险
and sometimes even risking their lives.
对我来说 他们是真正的英雄
To me, they are true heroes.
本集将讲述这些英雄的故事
This is the story of some of them.
安第斯山脉深处
Hidden in the heart of the Andes
隐藏着詹巴图研究中心
is the Centro Jambatu research centre.
它正在保护一些 也许会令人惊讶的
It's protecting members of what is, perhaps surprisingly,
世界上最濒危的动物群体
the most endangered group of animals in the world.
青蛙
Frogs.
它们是各自物种中 仅存的一些个体
These individuals are the very last of their particular species.
它们被带到这里的目的 不只是保护它们
They're brought here not only for protection,
更重要的是
but, more importantly,
让种群繁衍壮大
to increase their numbers.
而找到它们的人是
And the person to find them...
哈梅 · 库莱布拉斯
..Jaime Culebras.
我第一次见到青蛙时 只有7岁
I was seven the first time that I saw a frog
那一刻改变了我的一生
and just changed my life.
自那之后
And ever since his childhood,
他一直在探索最偏远的地方
he's been exploring the remotest places
寻找最稀有的青蛙
and searching for the rarest frogs.
这是只叶蛙
This is a leaf frog.
它太奇妙了
He is just amazing.
看到这样的动物 怎么能不爱它呢
It's impossible to don't fall in love with an animal like this, no?
这里有一只青蛙非常特别
But there is one frog here that is very special.
名字叫做悲情圣地亚哥
His name, Sad Santiago.
这是悲情圣地亚哥
This is Sad Santiago.
悲情是因为它非常孤单
He's sad because he's alone.
它是物种中的最后一员之一
He's one of the last members of his species.
它需要一只雌性伴侣
And he needs a female.
莫罗纳-圣地亚哥丑角蛙
Known as the Morona-Santiago harlequin frog,
它可能是世界上最稀有的青蛙
he may be the rarest frog in the world.
这里的其他青蛙都在尽可能
While the other frogs here are doing their best
增加种群数量
to increase their populations,
悲情圣地亚哥却孤零零等了四年
Santiago has sat alone for four long years.
也许它不是最漂亮的青蛙 但也值得被爱
Maybe it's not the most beautiful frog, but he deserves love.
悲情圣地亚哥已经老了
Santiago has now grown old,
如果哈梅不能尽快为它找到伴侣
and if Jaime can't find a female for him soon,
整个物种便可能就此灭绝
the whole species could become extinct.
这种青蛙最后的目击地点
The last place where one of these frogs was seen...
是在厄瓜多尔云雾森林的高山上
..was high up on a mountain in the cloud forest of Ecuador.
路只有一条
There's only one way to get there.
一同前往的还有青蛙猎人达尔文
Joining him is fellow frog-hunter Darwin
以及哈梅的伴侣 青蛙学家弗朗西斯卡
and Jaime's partner and frog scientist, Francesca.
哦
Oh!
快点
Come on, vamanos.
上去
Arriba.
这是地球上最潮湿的地方之一
This is one of the wettest places on Earth,
而且现在正是雨季
and right now it's actually the wet season, the rainy season,
雨水更多
so it rains even more.
潮湿且到处都是虫子
Soaking wet and teeming with bugs...
这里是青蛙的理想家园
..it's a perfect place for frogs.
出发
Let's go.
大多数青蛙夜晚才会现身
Most frogs come out of hiding at night.
这个地方太奇妙了
This place is extremely wonderful.
但需要时刻小心
But you have to be careful where you put your hands.
和他在一起
Being with him is...
很特别
..it's unusual.
这段关系很特别
It's not your regular relationship.
他对青蛙非常着迷
Oh, he's obsessed. He's really obsessed.
这样的溪流可能隐藏着许多
Streams like this should be full of frogs
各种各样的青蛙
of many different species...
但他们找了整夜 却一无所获
..but they search all night and find nothing.
整片森林鸦雀无声
It's a silent forest.
很悲哀
It's sad.
青蛙的歌声 正渐渐消逝
The sound of frogs is slowly disappearing from our world.
如今 很多青蛙物种
The only place many frog species can now be found
只能在博物馆中找到
is in a museum.
一个关键原因 在于一种叫做壶菌的真菌的蔓延
A key reason is the spread of a fungus called chytrid...
它能寄生在青蛙的湿润皮肤上
..that can grow on the moist skins of frogs,
最终致其死亡
eventually killing them.
据估计 90种青蛙因此而灭绝
90 species are thought to have become extinct as a consequence,
还有近600种青蛙 正面临极高的灭绝风险
and almost 600 more are now critically endangered.
如果没有壶菌 我敢保证
Before chytrid, I'm pretty sure that you could walk
这条小溪将到处都是
through the stream and see everywhere
趴在石头上的各种青蛙
many, many, many frogs on the rocks,
呱呱大叫
calling "prrr-prrr"!
我多希望我生活在壶菌病之前
I wish I had been born before the frog disease.
夜复一夜
Night after night...
他们在小溪四处搜寻
..they search the stream.
哈梅
Jaime!
终于 有了一个发现
At last, there is a discovery.
声音是
The sound is a...
我不确定具体在哪 但大概就在这里
I don't know exactly where, but it's there, more or less.
在水里
En el agua!
抓到了
We have it.
一只玻璃蛙
A glass frog.
一只非常漂亮的玻璃蛙
A really beautiful glass frog.
玻璃蛙如今越来越稀少
Glass frogs are becoming increasingly rare,
也许某一天便会彻底灭绝
and one day they, too, could disappear.
但团队寻找的目标不是它
But it's not what they are looking for.
事实上 很多物种悄无声息地灭绝
The fact is that countless species go extinct...
鲜有人知
..unnoticed.
哈梅唯一能做的 便是继续寻找
All Jaime can do is to continue his search
悲情圣地亚哥的伴侣
for a mate for Santiago.
在那里吗
It's there?
我找到了一只雌性
I found a female!
啊
Agh!
太棒了
Woohoo!
是只雌性 看啊
It's a female! Look.
体型比雄性大一些
The size is bigger than the males.
哇
Wow.
我太高兴了
I feel so happy!
第一只雌性
The first female!
这只雌蛙将成为新繁殖计划的关键
She could be the cornerstone of a new breeding programme.
悲情圣地亚哥彻底不悲情了
Santiago will be very, very, very, very, very happy.
这只雌蛙特别漂亮
Because she's really beautiful!
我手上拎着希望
In my hand, I have hope.
是这个物种的救星
I have the saviour of this species,
也是繁殖计划的救星
for breeding programmes and for people to reproduce it.
说不清 感觉希望就捧在我手上
I don't know, it's like I just have hope in my hand.
世上有7000多种青蛙
There are over 7,000 species of frogs in the world,
可能会有人疑惑
and you may well ask...
就算有几种消失了 又有什么大不了的
..does it really matter if a few go extinct?
可是 看看这种小小的
Well, just look at this tiny species
箭毒蛙
of poison arrow frog.
科学家发现它皮肤上的化学物质
Scientists discovered a chemical on its skin...
镇痛效果是吗啡的200倍
..200 times stronger than morphine.
如今科学家正在深入研究 以开发强效止痛药
Now they are studying how it works to create powerful new painkillers.
但大自然远不只是一个药箱那么简单
But the natural world is not just one vast medicine chest.
它有着无可替代的重要性
It's far more than that.
大自然是我们的生命之源
It is our life support system,
是世界的基石
the fabric that holds our world together.
如果我们失去了大自然的一部分
Remove a part of it, a species or a habitat,
将会造成未知的后果
and there's no knowing what could happen.
典型的例子 非洲森林象
A prime example is the forest elephant.
它们是非洲雨林的
They play a crucial role in maintaining
重要组成部分
the rainforests of Africa...
它们帮助植物传播种子
..dispersing seeds and making clearings
为其他动物创造生存空间
that are then used by many other animals.
2004年 我们为第一部《地球脉动》
We filmed these images in 2004
拍摄了这些画面
for the first Planet Earth series.
九年后 偷猎者为了象牙
Nine years later, poachers came here
猎杀了26头森林象
and killed 26 elephants for their ivory...
其中还有4只小象
..including four of the calves.
自那之后
Since that first series,
非洲森林象的数量
the number of forest elephants across Africa
减少了三分之二
has dropped by two-thirds.
但阻止偷猎的工作十分危险
But stopping the slaughter is a risky business.
非洲西部 科特迪瓦 阿比让
Abidjan, in Cote d'Ivoire, West Africa...
是非法象牙交易的一个节点
..part of the global network in the illegal ivory trade.
一名女性来到此处
A stranger has flown in from Vietnam,
她来自象牙的重要进口国 越南
a hub for the import of ivory.
大象是我最爱的动物
Elephant is my favourite animal on earth.
看到它们这样被猎杀
Seeing how they are being killed
真的很让我难过
that just really upset me
我想做些力所能及的事情
and I just want to do something - anything I can.
她的名字是阮庄
Her name - Trang Nguyen.
她假装是象牙买家
Her speciality - infiltrating the illegal wildlife trade
打入非法野生动物交易内部
by posing as a buyer.
我得稍微改变一下性格
I have to change my character a bit
因为通常我很健谈
because normally I'm very chatty
喜欢笑 喜欢与人交谈
and I like to smile, and I like to talk to people
但我必须变得冷漠刻薄
but I have to be cold, and I have to be mean.
你身边都是罪犯
When you're going in, you're dealing with criminals.
依靠谎话
You're telling lies.
假装自己是一个买家
You have to pretend to be someone else.
如果不小心露馅了
If by accident you blow that cover
很可能就没命了
it's possible that I'll be killed.
阮庄和一个叫EAGLE的保护组织合作
Trang is working with a network of conservationists called EAGLE.
她的联络人是伦斯 · 伊尔根
Her contact here is Rens Ilgen.
这里的象牙交易有个特点
But what is particular with this new trade in West Africa is,
很多象牙都是小象的
as you can see, a lot of the tusks are from baby elephants.
这说明 幸存的大象已经所剩无几了
So, they're really down to the last elephants.
上周 有七个人被杀
Last week, seven people were killed.
七个护林员被杀吗
Seven ranger was killed?
所以显然 如今已经不仅是象牙交易的问题
So, clearly, it is not just about the ivory trade,
还有很多无辜的人 为了保护大象而失去生命
but a lot of people, rangers, that are being killed as well.
-简直是一场战争 -一场战争
It's...it's war. It's war.
-连刚出生的小象也不放过 -是啊
And they're even going for the baby elephants.  Yeah.
现在阮庄确定了自己的任务
Now Trang is set her task.
我希望你去见见象牙交易的首领
So, I want you to meet the godfather of ivory.
四年前 他因藏有400公斤象牙
We already arrested him four years ago
而被逮捕过一次
when he had 400kg of ivory,
那些象牙是提供给越南的
which he was supplying to the Vietnamese community
与当地黑帮有所牵连
linked to the Vietnamese mafia.
因为被抓过 所以他可能会很谨慎
As he has been arrested before, he might be very cautious.
任务可能会很危险
It might be dangerous.
她打扮成一名商人
She prepares her disguise as a businesswoman -
但衣服下
but under her jacket,
藏有录音设备
hidden recording equipment.
保护组织已经秘密跟踪
EAGLE's undercover agents have been following
象牙组织首领好几年了
the godfather for years.
现在是时候将他绳之以法了
Now is the moment to catch him.
这是第一次会面
This is your first meeting.
只是聊聊天 互相了解一下
You're just going to discuss and get to know each other.
-看看他们有没有货 -没错
See if they have the products. Exactly.
我进去后
I'm going in,
要背对门坐着
and I need to sit facing away from the door,
因为不能让别人看见我在这里
because I don't want people to see me with him.
-我们就在附近 -好的
We will be close by...  Yep.
一定会很顺利的
..and nothing will go wrong.
好的
OK.
祝你好运
Good luck.
再见
Bye.
她在一个当地的咖啡馆与组织首领会面
She meets the godfather at a local cafe.
晚上好
Good evening.
秘密摄像机拍下了一切
The secret cameras capture the story.
很高兴见到你
Nice to meet you.
久仰大名
I've heard a lot about you.
我正在寻找
I'm looking for opportunities
在这里做生意的机会
to start working and doing business over here.
你在找合作伙伴
So you need someone to help you in your business?
他们想知道你到底需要什么
So they want to know exactly what you need from us.
我的需要
Need?
是的
Yes.
我听说你们有一些有意思的货
I heard that you have some interesting products
是我想要的
that i want.
对吗
Right?
她在说什么
What is she talking about?
具体是什么
As what?
象牙
As elephant ivory.
然而组织首领矢口否认
But the godfather denies having any ivory for sale.
我们只做木材 不做象牙交易
We can't do ivory because we only work in wood.
我们能搞到
So we can get it here
但现在不行
but now, no.
目前来说
For the time being
是不可能的
it's not possible.
谢谢
Merci.
是的
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
谢谢
Merci.
也许他真的没有象牙
Perhaps there's no ivory.
或者也许他不信任阮庄
Or maybe he doesn't trust Trang.
这是个巨大的挫折
It's a serious setback.
但还有其他象牙贩子
But there are other traders out there.
阮庄的出现也许会引起他们的注意
Perhaps her presence in town will draw them in.
每过一天
Every day that passes,
就有更多的大象被杀害
more elephants are killed.
对于阮庄来说 这份工作和她的生命有关
For Trang, this work is very personal.
我23岁时 接到了一通电话
When I was 23, I got the phone call.
医生告诉我 我患有结肠癌
The doctor told me that I had bowel cancer.
我当时第一个念头是 我还这么年轻
The first thing pop up in my mind is that I'm so young,
怎么会得癌症呢
well, how can I get cancer?
一旦患上癌症
Once you have cancer,
就不知道自己还能活多久
you don't know how long you're going to live for,
如果有什么想做的事情 就趁现在去做吧
and if I want to do anything, then I should just do it now.
因此我决定去做卧底
And that's when I said, "OK, I'm just going to do undercover,"
因为我不知道自己什么时候会死
because I don't know when I'm going to die.
我想做一些有意义的事情
I might as well do something really meaningful.
目前 阮庄的病情得到了缓解
Currently, Trang is in remission.
三天后 事情有了突破
Three days later, there's a breakthrough.
一个卖家发来了视频
A video sent by a trader.
视频里大约有14 15根象牙
I can see that this video have about 14, 15 ivory.
有大有小
They are big tusks, they are also small tusks as well.
毫无疑问是从小象身上割下来的
It's obviously come from baby elephants.
卖家上钩了
The bait has been taken.
阮庄以及EAGLE团队必须迅速采取行动
Trang and the EAGLE team must act fast.
她前去与新目标会面
She goes to meet the new targets.
首先
First job...
晚上好
Bonsoir.
要取得他们的信任
..gain their trust.
干杯
Cheers.
Cheers.  Cheers.
我们有一间房
We have a hotel room.
可以去那里
Let us go there.
给货物称重
We need to weigh how much the items are
一手交钱 一手交货
and then we just give the money
各取所需
He goes his way, I go my way.
成交
Done.
最后 阮庄说服卖家来到
Eventually, Trang persuades the traders to move to
附近的一家酒店
a hotel room nearby...
给象牙称重 完成交易
..to weigh the ivory and make the transaction.
关上门
Close the door. Close the door.
品相很好
It's good.
象牙按重量计价
Ivory is sold by the kilo.
这些有20多公斤
That is just over 20.
20.2
20.2?
20.3
20.3.
整个大象家族因此而被杀
A whole elephant family was killed for this haul.
价值超过5000英镑
It's worth over £5,000.
在这里 这相当于一整年的收入
Here, that is a year's salary.
然而卖家并不知道
What the traders don't realise...
警察就在楼上待命
..is that the police are in the room above,
等待阮庄的消息
waiting for a text from Trang.
行动
OK, let's go.
是谁
Who's there?
客房服务
It's reception.
Service?
是谁
Who is it?
客房服务
It's reception.
好的 等一下
Okay, just a minute please.
你去开门
You go open the door.
好
OK.
就放这里
Just put it down here.
警察 警察
Police! Police!
不许动 不许动
Don't move, don't move, don't move!
趴下
Lie down!
不许动
Don't move!
手放在背后
Hands behind your back!
我什么都不知道
I don't know, I don't know, I don't know!
这是什么
What's this?
我不知道
I don't know!
为了保护阮庄的安全
For her own safety,
她必须继续装作犯罪分子
she has to keep her cover story and behave as a criminal...
因此她也必须被逮捕
..which means she must also be arrested.
闭嘴
Shut up!
象牙全球供应链的一个节点
A link in the global supply chain...
被切断了
..broken.
阮庄被迅速带走
Trang is whisked away,
而卖家则被送到警察局
whilst the traders are taken to the police station,
对她的卧底身份毫不知情
none the wiser about her involvement.
在接下来的一年 EAGLE在打击全球野生动物贸易的斗争中
Over the next year, EAGLE catch 140 more traffickers
抓获了140多名非法交易人员
in the fight against the global wildlife trade.
但对于阮庄来说 这是她的最后一次行动
But for Trang, this is her last operation.
因此我们能够拍摄她的面孔
It's why we can show her face.
我从事卧底工作
I have been doing undercover work
参与诱捕行动有一段时间了
and sting operations for quite a while
压力确实很大
and it can be really stressful.
她不能再逗留在这里了
It's not safe for her to stay a minute longer than necessary.
阮庄的最后一项任务 就是从阿比让
Trang's final task is to vanish from Abidjan...
彻底消失
..for ever.
世界各地 野生动物的数量正以惊人的速度减少
Across the world, the numbers of wild animals are falling alarmingly.
短短二十年里
In just two decades -
也就是自从第一部《地球脉动》
since we started making the first Planet Earth series -
全球野生动物的数量
the abundance of wildlife around the globe has dropped,
平均下降了超过30%
on average, by over 30%.
我们正面临一场灾难 一场浩劫
We're facing a disaster, a catastrophe.
科学家认为 我们正处在物种大灭绝的边缘
Scientists say that we're on the edge of a mass extinction.
而这正是人类活动造成的
It's being caused by human activity.
因此 人类也有能力阻止这一切
So humans also have the power to stop it.
拯救物种的艰巨任务 需要很多品质
It takes many qualities to save even one species.
决心
Determination...
勇气
..courage...
以及热情
..and passion.
同时 往往还需要一种品质
And often, there's another ingredient that's needed...
放眼未来 敢于创新
..the ability to think big.
在维也纳 凯瑟琳娜 · 赫切勒开始了一份新工作
In Vienna, Katharina Huchler is just starting a new job.
工资很低
The pay is terrible.
工作时间很长
The hours are long.
而且没有休息日
And there are no days off.
她将成为一名寄养母亲
She is about to become a foster mother.
嗨
Hi.
早上好
Good morning.
嗨
Hi. Hi.
这些是她的新宝宝
And these are her new babies...
你好有精神 嗨
You're pretty awake. Hi.
28只世界上最稀有的鸟类之一
..28 of one of the world's rarest birds.
嘿 你好
Hey. Hi.
隐鹮
The northern bald ibis.
你会很快爱上它们的
You really quickly fall in love with them.
400多年前在欧洲 隐鹮被猎杀殆尽
They were hunted to extinction in Europe over 400 years ago.
这些雏鸟是在动物园出生的
These chicks were born in a zoo.
凯瑟琳娜的任务 是教它们
Katharina's task is to teach them
如何在野外生存 自由飞翔
to become wild, free birds.
来吧来吧
Yes, yes, yes. Komm. Komm.
为此 她必须让雏鸟相信 自己是它们的母亲
To do that, she must convince them that she is their mother.
这是一个叫做印随的过程
It's a process called imprinting.
这期间 不能让雏鸟看到或听到
While it's happening, the chicks must never see or hear
除了海伦娜的任何人或者声音
any other human except Helena,
海伦娜是第二次成为隐鹮的寄养母亲
who's an ibis foster mum for the second time.
她们必须穿着完全相同的黄色服装
They must always wear identical yellow clothes
并且不停发出相同的声音
and repeat the same noises again and again.
我们模仿成年隐鹮的声音 像是
We mimic the sounds the adults make, it's like...
我的模仿还不够好
But I'm not good yet at doing it!
晚安
Goodnight.
她们陪着雏鸟直到睡着
They're here when the chicks fall asleep...
做个好梦
Sleep well.
雏鸟醒来一睁眼看到的也是她们
..and the first thing they see when they awake.
早上好
Good morning, waldies! Hallo!
去吃点早饭吧 好不好
Let's have something to eat, shall we? Yes, let's eat.
它们有点像人类宝宝
They're a bit like every human baby.
它们需要一天从早到晚
They just need their food bit by bit by bit
一口一口吃饭
all day long.
很好很好
Yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes.
糟了 出错了
Oh, no, we did it all wrong!
就跟给宝宝换尿布一样
It's really like changing the nappies of the babies.
负责28只雏鸟的吃喝拉撒
28 mouths to feed and bottoms to wipe,
还要不断跟雏鸟交流
and all the time talking to the birds.
来吧来吧
Komm, komm, waldies! Komm, komm!
感觉很累
Feeling really tired.
想多睡一会儿
Yeah, I'd really like to sleep a little bit more.
随着时间的流逝 他们的感情越来越深
As the weeks pass, the bond grows.
接下来 雏鸟要进入
And then it is time for their next stage
成为野生隐鹮的新阶段
in becoming wild birds.
他们来到奥地利阿尔卑斯山的一片草地上
They move to a field in the Austrian Alps.
雏鸟已经长出了可以飞行的羽毛
They've now grown their adult flight feathers...
但它们内心还只是雏鸟
...but they're still chicks on the inside.
因此 印随工作还要继续
So the imprinting must continue.
我们用这个手势
With this hand gesture we do,
模仿成年隐鹮的喙
we imitate the bill of an adult ibis
并配合隐鹮的叫声
and we combine it with the greeting sound.
像这样
So, this is...
这样的模仿是出于一个重要的原因
All this imprinting is for a very important reason.
隐鹮是候鸟
These are migratory birds.
秋季 它们必须飞往南方
In autumn, they must fly south
飞往位于意大利的温暖觅食地
to their warm feeding grounds in Italy.
而这是个问题
And that is a problem.
它们知道自己必须去往某个地方
They know that they need to go somewhere,
但不知道往哪个方向飞 要飞多远
but they don't know in which direction and how far.
它们需要从父母那里学习迁徙路线
So they need to learn the route from their parents.
现在这成了寄养母亲的工作
Their human mothers must show them the way.
而这需要一点创意
And that requires a little ingenuity.
是时候检验印随的效果了
This is where the imprinting is put to the test.
如果她们坐在一架飞机上
Will the birds follow them...
隐鹮会跟着她们吗
..even in a microlight?
来吧来吧
Komm, komm!
来吧来吧鸟儿们
Komm, komm, waldies!
来吧来吧
Komm, komm!
来吧来吧鸟儿们
Come come, ibis! Come, come!
过近的距离对于隐鹮和人都很危险
Getting too close is dangerous for both birds and humans.
有只鸟飞在绳索间
There's a bird in the lines!
其他都飞在前面
The others are all at the front.
有只鸟飞得太近了
There's one near the lines.
靠近左侧的绳索
Close to the lines on the left.
没问题了
It's all fine.
尽管开头不太顺利
After a wobbly start...
但最终隐鹮老实了下来
..at last they settle.
出发
Let's go!
印随工作大成功
The imprinting has worked.
隐鹮今天表现非常好
Our birds did very well today.
但最大的挑战还在后面
But their biggest challenge is still to come.
齐勒塔尔阿尔卑斯山脉
The Zillertal Alps.
岩石和冰雪组成巨大的一堵墙
A great wall of rock and ice.
这将是隐鹮生命中
It's going to be the most important flight
最重要的一次飞行
of their young lives.
这将会让它们精疲力竭
It will take them to the very edge of exhaustion.
很多年轻的鸟在第一次迁徙时 失去了性命
A lot of young birds die during their first migration.
它们过于缺乏经验
They are still so inexperienced.
这对于寄养母亲和飞行员来说同样危险
There's also danger for the foster mothers and the pilots.
如果飞机出了问题
If there is a problem with the microlights,
根本没有安全的地方着陆
there is no safe place to land.
要想飞越这些山峰
To gain enough height to fly over these mountains...
它们必须找到叫做热气流的上升气流
..they must find columns of rising air called thermals.
这种技术往往需要鸟儿
A skill these birds would normally learn
在跟随父母迁徙时习得
by following their natural mothers.
找到上升气流 需要精湛的飞行技术
It takes expert piloting to find the thermals.
而上升气流中
Once within one,
气流猛烈 难以控制
it's turbulent and unpredictable.
高度很高了
We're very high now.
每次转弯 她们都要确认
With every turn, the mothers must make sure
28只隐鹮是否都跟上了
all 28 birds are following.
有一只脱离大部队了
One's separate from the others.
28只隐鹮都在
All 28 birds here.
最终 它们飞过了最高的山峰
At last, they make it over the highest ridge.
从此以后 飞行就轻松多了
From now on, it should be easy flying.
我们的目的 不仅是拯救隐鹮
What we are trying to do, apart from saving the ibis,
还是给人们带来希望
is trying to give hope to people.
如果你可以让一个物种重获新生
If you can bring back one species,
其他物种自然同样可以
you can also do it with others.
曾经濒临灭绝的物种 如今再度振翅高飞
A species once left for dead now has a future.
它们飞向自然保护区
And they head for their safe winter home
那里将成为它们安全的冬季家园
in a protected nature reserve.
但正如在这个系列中看到的
But as we have seen throughout this series,
许多物种正在失去它们赖以生存的野生栖息地
many species are losing the wild habitats they need to survive.
而这正是导致灭绝的最大原因
It's the biggest cause of extinction.
这一点在亚马逊雨林中最为明显
Nowhere is this more apparent than in the Amazon rainforest.
二十年里 《地球脉动》摄制组
Our Planet Earth crews have filmed here many times
多次在这里拍摄
over the last two decades.
而这段时间里 超过160亿颗树
And in that time, over 16,000 million trees...
遭到砍伐
..have been felled.
为了保护生活在此的无数物种
To safeguard the countless species that live here...
雨林本身必须得到保护
..the forest itself must be protected..
而有一股力量 正为此而崛起
And there's a force rising up to do just that.
瞧这只蚂蚁 贝拉
Look at this ant, Bella
孤零零一只蚂蚁
This ant is all alone.
脆弱无助
It's helpless.
但蚂蚁群团结一心
But when they are all together
便攻无不克
they are strong.
亚历珊德拉 · 科拉普是蒙杜鲁库族的领袖之一
Alessandra Korap is one of the leaders of the Munduruku.
他们是这部分亚马逊的守护者
They have been the guardians of this part of the Amazon
有着数千年的历史
for thousands of years.
我们蒙杜鲁库族人
We, the Munduruku
是这片森林的一部分
we are part of this forest
我们必须像蚂蚁一样团结一心
and we must keep being like this little ant.
对抗破坏森林的人
We have to keep bothering people.
我爱这片森林
I love this forest!
既是市场 又是药房
It's a market, it's a pharmacy.
但这片森林不仅仅只属于蒙杜鲁库族
But the forest is not just there for the Munduruku.
而是属于整个地球
It's there for the planet.
亚历珊德拉小时候 这片亚马逊森林
When she was a child, this part of the Amazon forest
是一望无际的处女地
stretched unbroken for hundreds of miles.
但如今它被割成碎片
Now it's being carved up...
为了矿产与木材
..for mining, for timber,
而最主要的是为了农业
but most of all for agriculture.
这里是亚马逊保卫战的前线
This is the front line in the battle for the Amazon,
这场战争沾满了血泪
and it is a deadly one.
过去的十年里 巴西有超过300人
In the last decade, more than 300 people have been murdered
为保护环境而死
in Brazil defending the environment.
保护森林时
When you protect a forest
总是会面临生命危险
our lives are at stake.
我随时可能失去生命
I could be killed at any moment.
他们两次试图杀死我
They tried to kill me twice
试图杀害其他部落领袖
They tried to kill other leaders
被关在屋子里 活活烧死
by burning them alive, inside their house.
像许多原住民群体一样
The Munduruku, like many indigenous groups,
蒙杜鲁库族与世隔绝
live in isolated communities
经常遭到开采 农业和伐木等活动的侵扰
vulnerable to attack from miners, farmers and loggers.
伐木工人来到这里
The loggers are coming in.
总是拿着枪走来走去
They always go around with their gunmen.
很多部落里的人
A lot of people don't know what's happening
不知道发生了什么
here in the territory.
因此他们以为这是我们编造出来的谎言
So they think it's a lie, that we're making it up.
为什么要砍这么多树呢
Why do they have to cut down so much?
亚马逊的未来 是由远在3200公里外的巴西政府决定的
The Amazon's future is decided 2,000 miles away.
在这里 议员正在讨论
Here, in the parliament of Brazil,
制定新的法案 允许对原住民土地
new laws are being debated to allow the exploitation
进行商业开发
of their traditional tribal land.
但亚历珊德拉不甘于此
But Alessandra has a plan -
她计划联合其他部落
to unite with other tribes
发起一场规模空前的抗议
and organise a protest so big
让政府听到他们的声音
that it cannot be ignored.
我们需要做好准备
We need to prepare ourselves
前往城市
to go to the city.
当我们离开家园
When we leave our home
前往首都巴西利亚时
to go to Brasilia
我们发现了许多敌人
we find many enemies.
西装革履的人
And the ones who wear suits
正在制造战争 制定法律
are making war, making laws.
我们曾经用弓箭
Before we used to use arrows
保卫我们的领地
to fight for our territory.
如今一切都不一样了
Today is different.
这趟前往首都的旅程 将花费三天
It's a three-day journey to the capital city.
曾经雨林覆盖的土地
Trucks rumble to and from the fields...
如今变成了农田
..land that used to be rainforest.
隆隆的卡车装满了大豆
They're carrying thousands of tonnes of soya beans.
从亚马逊深处运往世界各地
It's shipped from the heart of the Amazon across the world.
这些大豆不是用来养活人类
Not to feed humans...
而是用来喂养家畜
..but to feed livestock.
我们的森林
Our forest,
我们的亚马逊
our Amazon,
遭到严重破坏
is being destroyed
就只是为了养鸡 养猪
for you to have your chicken farm, your pig farm.
最终 亚历珊德拉抵达了巴西利亚
Eventually, Alessandra makes it to Brasilia.
她的抗议行动引起了全国的关注
News of the protest has spread all over the country.
有200个不同的部落加入了她的行列
200 groups have united in a huge camp.
有来自巴西东北部的苏库鲁人
From the northeast of Brazil - the Xukuru.
有来自亚马逊南部的卡拉加人
From the southern edge of the Amazon - the Karaja.
如果我们同意这项法案
If we decide now to agree to the approval of this law
就等于将我们的子孙后代置之死地
then we are agreeing to the deaths of our children.
抗议活动持续了十天
For ten days, they protest against the proposed laws.
我觉得我们就像小蚂蚁 与国家机器斗争
I see us as little ants, fighting against the machine.
但当我们团结起来
But when we get together
他们就不得不重视
then we start to bother them.
就会听见我们的声音 感受到我们的力量
Then they feel it, then they hear it.
亚历珊德拉和其他部落领袖
Alessandra and the other leaders have created
掀起了巴西历史上 最大的原住民抗议活动
the biggest protest by indigenous people ever held in Brazil.
最终努力没有白费 其中一项法案被推翻了
Later, one of the proposed laws was withdrawn.
这是亚历珊德拉为保护巴西自然资源
A small but significant victory
取得的一个虽小 却意义重大的胜利
in Alessandra's fight for Brazil's wild places.
目前 野生动物面临的最大危机
The destruction of habitats is currently the biggest threat
是栖息地的丧失
to the survival of animal species.
然而 更大的危机正在逼近
But there is an even greater disaster on the horizon.
那就是气候变化
Our climate is changing.
季节变得越来越不稳定且极端
Seasons have become unpredictable and more extreme.
地球正在变暖
Our planet is getting hotter.
科学家预测 如果全球气温上升
Scientists predict that if the global temperature
超过2摄氏度
rises by over two degrees,
那么气候变化就可能成为 导致物种灭绝的最主要原因
it is likely to become the number one cause of extinction.
要阻止气候变化
To halt climate change,
也许需要政客们自身也成为英雄
perhaps politicians need to become heroes, too.
大家晚上好 欢迎来到格拉斯哥
Hello, good evening, and a warm welcome to Glasgow
参加这场期待已久的气候峰会 COP26的开幕
and the start of the long-awaited climate summit, COP26.
各国领导人 杰出的科学家
World leaders, prominent scientists
都已做好准备
and advisers all ready for 12 days of...
默罕默德 · 纳希德是一名政治家
Mohamed Nasheed is a politician,
曾担任马尔代夫的总统
the former president of the Maldives.
医生说 他们从我身上
The doctors said that they took 16 ball bearings
取出了16颗钢珠
from all parts of my body.
我昏迷了两天
I was unconscious for two days.
他的政治生涯充满艰辛 经受过酷刑 牢狱之灾
Over his political career, he has been tortured, imprisoned
并且刚刚在刺杀下逃过一劫
and recently survived an assassination attempt.
但这期间
But during that time,
他也一直在为应对气候变化而奋斗
he's also fought relentlessly against climate change.
很荣幸邀请默罕默德 · 纳希德
..pleasure to be able to bring you Mohamed Nasheed.
在格拉斯哥气候峰会COP26的前一天
In Glasgow, on the eve of climate conference COP26,
他在一个集会上发表了演讲
he is addressing a rally.
谢谢
Thank you.
非常感谢
Thank you very much.
我们来到COP26
So, we come to COP26
是为了探索人类的未来
to find out whether we still have a future.
如果我们不能签署一个有法律效力的协议
If we cannot have a legally binding agreement
阻止全球气温升高
not to push global temperatures
超过1.5度
above 1.5 degrees,
我的祖国就将彻底消失
my country will be gone,
世界上所有珊瑚礁和大部分雨林
as will all the world's coral reefs
也会随之消亡
and most of the rainforests.
仅仅为了能在短短几年内
Is all this devastation really worth it,
继续燃烧煤炭以及化石燃料
so that we can continue to burn coal and fossil fuel
而引发如此灾难 真的值得吗
for a few more years?
我一生
I have spent a lifetime
都在为我的国家而战
fighting for my country,
而且我现在比以往任何时候都更有决心
and with more determination than ever,
因为我清楚 我生活在这颗美丽星球上的时间可能已经不多了
because I know my time on Earth might be cut short.
默罕默德 · 纳希德对大自然的热爱
Mohamed Nasheed's passion for the natural world
始于他第一次见到珊瑚礁
began the first time he saw a coral reef.
我最早的记忆
My earliest memory
就是与海洋和珊瑚礁在一起
is with the ocean and the reef.
我们是第一代真正见到珊瑚礁的人
We were the first generation to actually see the reef.
潜水面罩和护目镜在60年代末
Masks and goggles came to the Maldives
70年代初出现在马尔代夫
in the late '60s, early '70s.
一旦把珊瑚礁看作一个活着的生物
Once we started seeing the reef as a living creature...
我们就会惊叹不已
..we were just dumbfounded.
然而纳希德深爱的珊瑚礁
But Nasheed's beloved coral is now the habitat
如今是受气候变化威胁最大的栖息地
that is most threatened by climate change.
温度上升的临界值是1.5度
The critical tipping point is a 1.5 degree temperature rise.
一旦高过这个数字 大多数珊瑚礁将死亡
Beyond that, most reefs will die,
留下一片废墟
leaving nothing but rubble.
当你把目光放的长远
When you think of a bigger picture,
自己一个人的生命便不再那么重要了
then your own life is not so important.
重要的是能在生命中做些什么
It's what you want to get done which is important.
纳希德的目标 是说服政治家减少使用
Nasheed's aim is to persuade politicians to cut the use
煤炭和其他化石燃料
of coal and other fossil fuels.
他在每个气候会议上 都重复着这份诉求
He repeats this plea at every climate conference.
你必须说服人们
You need to be able to convince people,
引导人们
try to educate people.
我们处于危机之中
We are in trouble.
如果地球气温升高超过1.5度 人类将无法生存
We will not survive if the planet is heated above 1.5 degrees.
我们必须立刻采取行动
We must act now.
一开始 有些国家领导人
At first, journalists are reporting on some eye-catching promises
做出了引人注目的承诺
made by heads of state.
18个国家承诺
18 countries have committed themselves
制定一个停止使用燃煤发电厂的计划
to a plan to stop using coal-fired power plants.
如今这是一个关乎选举的问题
It is an election issue now.
因此国家领导人才会做出这样的承诺
That is why world leaders have joined the rhetoric.
下一阶段 将承诺落实为具体计划
The next stage - turning promises into solid plans.
纳希德正在幕后努力推动这些计划
And Nasheed is busy working behind the scenes.
如果他们不同意 我们就给总统以及部长打电话
If they don't agree, we will ring their ministers, their presidents
在线上谈判
and get them online.
这就是我们要做的事情
I think that's what we're trying to do.
立刻行动吧
So let's do this.
你好 总理
How are you, Prime Minister?
我听得很清楚
Yeah, OK.  I can hear you,
但我听总理的声音更清楚
but I can hear the Prime Minister much clearer.
所有国家都要签署最终的协议
All countries need to agree to the final text -
但有些国家拒绝了
and some won't.
坚持使用化石燃料的人
People who want to continue fossil fuel,
我认为 是坏人
I think, are the bad guys.
而那些愿意做出改变的人 我则认为是好人
And people who want to change, I feel, are the good guys.
谢谢 非常感谢
Thank you. Thank you so much.
14天后 COP26闭幕
After 14 days, this COP closes...
虽然取得了一些进展
..with some progress,
但也有许多妥协
but also with big compromises.
一份协议中关于煤炭使用的关键部分
An agreement was finally reached this evening
在最后一刻被加以修改 放宽标准
after a key section on the future use of coal
才终于得到通过
was at the last moment watered down.
关键的新提案被搁置
Without urgent new commitments,
1.5度的目标将无法实现
the target of 1.5 degrees will be missed.
简直是灾难
It is disastrous.
这将
It will...
想象一下 如果你能理解这一切
If you picture this, if you can fathom it...
珊瑚礁将白化
..the coral will bleach
最终死去
and they will die,
而当珊瑚礁死亡
and when they are dead,
其中的鱼类以及海洋生命
the fish and the marine life that lives there...
也将不复存在
..cease to exist.
你本以为你的总理
You would have thought that your normal prime minister
和总统
and president...
能更好的理解这一切的重要性
..would have a better grip on understanding things.
而不是一味地坚持
And not just go on and on and on
维护自己的生活方式
about protecting their way of life.
所以看到那些政客如此无知
So it's frustrating to see politicians...
真的很让人沮丧
..who doesn't seem to understand it.
根据现行的政策
With current policies,
99%的珊瑚礁将在30年内
99% of coral reefs could be gone...
彻底消失
..in under 30 years.
其他的生态系统也将随之衰败
Other habitats will follow.
不能因此失去希望
You can't lose hope.
也不能因此而放弃
You cannot give up.
我不会停下脚步
I will not stop.
纳希德相信存在一个解决方案
Nasheed believes there is a solution.
随着环境问题逐渐成为选举的重点
The more environment becomes an election issue,
会有越来越多领导人采取行动应对气候变化
there will be more action on climate.
请把你手中每一张选票
Every time you vote, in every election,
都投给我们美丽的地球
please tick the planet.
拯救物种的艰巨任务不能只靠
The challenge of saving species can't be left to a few
在逆境中奋斗的少数英雄人物
heroic individuals working against the odds.
拥有更大权力的人
It's those in positions of great power
才能做出更大的改变
who can make the most difference.
因此 最终他们必须担起最大的责任
So, ultimately, it is they who must take the most responsibility.
也许我们的职责之一 便是向他们问责
Perhaps one of our roles is to hold them to account.
对于很多物种来说 时间已所剩无几
Time is running out for many species,
但我真心相信 如果现在在这个关键时刻
but I truly believe that if the right decisions are made now,
能做出正确的决定
at this critical moment,
所有生命仍有一个光明的未来
there could still be a bright future for all life
在我们美丽的地球上生生不息 脉动不止
on our wonderful planet Earth.
自本纪录片拍摄以来
悲情圣地亚哥辞世
但它的物种群落日益壮大
六十只隐鹮振翅 踏上了迁徙的征程
纳希德坚持在气候峰会上不断提出诉求
阮庄投身于新一代卧底警探的培养工作
二十头黑犀被运至安全的家园
在巴西 六个原住民土地
如今依法受到保护
「栖息地探索者」生动地展现动物和它们的栖息地
Habitat Explorer brings animals and their habitats to life.
探索这个免费互动程序并制作折纸动物
Explore this free interactive, and make origami animals.
前往bbc.co.uk/planetearth3
Go to bbc.co.uk/planetearth3
点击链接进入开放大学
and follow the links to the Open University.
或者订购免费印刷版
Or to order a free printed version,
欢迎访问网站或拨打屏幕上的号码
visit the website or call the numbers on the screen.